"There are no second acts in American lives."
Bird is a drama, music film directed by Clint Eastwood.
Saxophone player Charlie ‘Bird’ Parker comes to New York in 1940 and
is quickly noticed for his remarkable way of playing.
He becomes a drug addict but his loving wife Chan tries to help him.
Charlie 'Bird' Parker, played by Forest Whitaker.
Chan Parker, played by Diane Venora.
Red Rodney, played by Michael Zelniker.
Dizzy Gillespie, played by Samuel E. Wright.
Buster Franklin, played by Keith David.
Brewster, played by Michael McGuire.
Bird is a 1988 American biographical musical drama film about jazz saxophonist Charlie "Bird"
Parker, directed and produced by Clint Eastwood and written by Joel Oliansky.
The film stars Forest Whitaker as Parker, and
Diane Venora as his wife Chan Parker.
It is constructed as a montage of scenes from Parker's life, from his
childhood in Kansas City, through his early death at the age of 34.
The film moves back and forth through Parker's history,
blending moments to find some truth to his life.
Much of the film revolves around his only grounding relationships with Chan, Bebop
pioneer trumpet player and band leader Dizzy Gillespie (Samuel E.
Wright), and his influence (both musically and into the world of heroin
addiction) on trumpet player Red Rodney (Michael Zelniker).
Despite a lukewarm commercial performance, the film was well received by critics, with
particular praise toward Whitaker's performance, which became his breakthrough role.
He won the Best Actor Award at the 1988 Cannes Film Festival and was nominated for Best Actor – Motion
Picture Drama at the 46th Golden Globe Awards, while Eastwood won the award for Best Director.
Cahiers du Cinéma ranked Bird at #5 on its end-of-year Top 10 List.
The film explores themes of jazz, heroin,
saxophone, biography, psychiatric hospital.
The tone is emotional.